who is Genghis Khan for you, for the Mongols my
кто для вас Чингисхан для монгол мой
hero is a national hero the greatest and the
герой национальный герой самый большой и
best hero and it was true yes
самый хороший герой а это ж правда было
that it seems like when Genghis Khan was and his
да что вроде когда был Чингисхан да его
empire then Moscow was captured it
империя то Москву захватили это монголам
belonged to the Mongols it turns out uh
принадлежало то получается ээ
when you Mongols already had
когда у вас у монголов уже была
writing you wrote yes the Russians still it
письменность вы писали да русские ещё
turns out lived in the swamp
получается в болото жили
salam aleikum oh salam aleikum where are you
салам алейкум о салам алейкум ты откуда
from Mongolia oh from Mongolia itself right yeah
из Монголии о из самой Монголии прямо да
cool and you Russia writes and you are
прикольно а у тебя Россия пишет а ты
Mongols I live in Russia and you live in Russia and
монголи я живу России а живёшь в России
why did you come to Russia well so that you could study
а зачем в Россию приехал ну чтобы учите
I am now here studying at a military institute what
я сейчас здесь учусь в военный институт
military institute are you studying for yes and you are a
на кого военный институт учишься да а ты
citizen of what country
гражданин какой страны
from Mongolia Mongolia and you are not
из Монголии монголия а тебя не
sent to fight against Ukraine
отправляют воевать против Украины
yes they are sent so how do you send
да отправляют так ты как ты отправляешь
I just can't understand you went to Mongolia it is not clear
я просто не могу понять ты в Монголию
incomprehensible now explain you to
непонятно непонятную сейчас объясни ты в
Ukraine they are sending you to fight in Ukraine
Украину в Украину тебя воевать
not this is not there
не этого нету
but I
а
understand and in what and who are you studying for
понял а на каком на кого ты учишься
m  bridge builder
м мостовик
who is a military bridge builder military bridge builder bridge
кто военный мостовик военный мостовик
builder - it's like pontoons like an engineer
мостовик- это как понтоны типа инженер
yes it means yes an engineer engineer means
да значит да инженер инженер значит
engineering troops to build to build in a bridge a
инженерные войска строить строить в мост
bridge I understood to lay bridges yeah well howl is
мост понял прокладывать мосты угу ну вою
not the most important thing interesting but how now
не самое главное интересно а как сейчас
listen and how do the Russians treat you to the
слушай а как россияне относятся к вам к
Mongols to the Buryats
монголам к бурятам
mm normally
мм нормально
they don't say that you are some kind of like that yeah yeah yeah yes there is
они не говорят что вы какие-то там вот
such a thing they don't like they don't
так дадада да да есть такое они не любят
like anyone except Russians yeah
они никого не любят кроме русских
you're right there is well there is a war how how to
да ты правшь есть ну там война как как
go war well you know a lot that the Russians
идти война ну много знаешь что русские
take Buryats and Mongols of different kinds who
берут бурятов да монголов разных которые
Kazakhs who live in Russia and throw
казахов которые живут в России и бросают
them to fight in Ukraine so that they die
их воевать в Украину чтобы они умирали
va and so on
ва и так далее
Buryats and so few are left there get
бурятов и так мало осталось там получа
they are your related peoples Buryats
они же ваши родственные народы буряты
Mutiki there at the front yeah and the women are
мутики там на фронте да да а женщины
alone there in Buryatia there are some villages
одни там в в Бурятии есть некоторые сёла
in which there are no men left yeah got it and
в которых мужчин уже не осталось
in Mongolia it turns out that there are
понял а у вас получается в Монголии что
no military institutes
нет военных институтов
yes there are but there is no such profession so
да есть но такой профессии нету поэтому
here I understood and it turns out in which
тут понял а это получается в каком
city  study close to Mongolia mm in
городе учишься близко к Монголии мм на
St. Petersburg in St. Petersburg
Санкт-Петербурге в Санкт-Петербурге
St. Petersburg wow yeah you have people
санкт-петербург ничего себе да это у вас
studying there from different countries yeah yeah
там с разных стран учится да да
cool
прикольно
you live far away from the front that you
ты далеко живёшь из из фронта что ты
live far away from the front far far away yeah and
далеко живёшь из фронта далеко далеко да
we have missiles sometimes missiles
а у нас ракеты бывают прилетают ракеты
or martyrs fly in yeah yeah yeah but
или шахеды угу
look you have Mongolia yeah with
а а а вот смотри вот у вас Монголия да с
whom if you are a military man from Mongolia with
кем вот если ты военный из Монголии с
whom Mongolia can fight
кем Монголия может воевать
with whom eh
с кем э
with China I think you have
с Китай помоему у вас получается и
neighbors only China first of all first of all
соседи только Китай са первую очередь
China
самый в первую очередь Китай
and why China and not Russia
а почему Китай а не Россия
I know it's political I'm not interested in anything about it
я знаю это политический я об этом ничего
and what contradictions do you have with China
не интересую а какие у вас с Китаем
protivite
протилите
against well disputes with China what do you have you didn't
против ну споры с Китаем какие у вас не
understand what because of
поняли то что
what should you fight with China
из-за чего вы с Китаем должны воевать
and they want our strange place in my opinion
а им хочется наше странно место по-моему
China wants Mongolia yeah yeah
монголию хочет Китай да да
but Russia doesn't want
а Россия не хочет
in my opinion yes it does Russia also wants
по-моему да хочет россия тоже хочет
Mongolia yeah yeah
Монголию да да
hmm somehow it turns out interesting that  yes
хм как-то интересно получается то есть
but you study in Russia and there are many like
но ты учишься в России а много таких как
you study in Russia there are
ты учишься в России
many like you study in Russia Mongols
много как ты учишься в России монголов
yes Mongol yes you are in St. Petersburg 300
да монгол да вы в Санкт-Петербурге 300
people study who are from Mongolia
людей учите которые из Монголии
cool and have already studied Russian here in
прикольно а русский язык учил уже тут в
Russia or in Mongolia
России или в Монголии
here in Russia for 2 years already that is you
тут в России уже 2 года то есть ты
came to Russia did not know Russian at all
приехал в Россию вообще не знал русский
yes previously did not study at all
язык да раньше вообще не учился
cool I know that your president of
прикольно я знаю что ваш президент
Mongolia or who is now or the
Монголии или который сейчас или
previous one he studied in Ukraine once
предыдущий он в Украине учился когда-то
studied in Ukraine yes your previous or
украине учился да ваш предыдущий или
current president of Mongolia well
современный президент Монголии
listen listen and who is who for you
слушай слушай а кто кто для вас
Genghis Khan for the Mongols
Чингисхан для монголо
who is Genghis Khan for you who is
кто Чингисхан для вас кто
this
это
very like ours that is very Rozhde he
очень как нашего то очень Рожде он
lived a long time ago he lived well I know that he
жил очень давно он жил ну я знаю что он
lived a long time ago and for you who is he a hero there
давно жил а для вас кто он герой там
national yes hero hero national
национальный да герой герой национальный
hero the biggest and the best
герой самый большой и самый хороший
hero and it was true yes that like
герой а это же правда было да что вроде
when Genghis Khan was yes his empire then
когда был Чингисхан да его империя то
Moscow was captured it
Москву захватили это монголам
belonged to the Mongols yes yes and what now uh
принадлежало да да а что сейчас ээ
Mongol that's for me Russians  chastolom
монгол вот это мне русские частолам
aleikum Russians often tell me that uh the
алейкум мне русские часто говорят что
Mongols were wild there they had no
вот ээ монголы там дикие у них не было
cities, nothing, no civilization yes but
ни городов ничего ни цивилизации да но у
Genghis Khan had cities
Чингисхана ж были города
and Karakarum yes it was white yes it
и Каракарум был да он бел бе был да то
turns out
получается
when you Mongols already had
когда у вас у монголов уже была
writing you wrote yes Russians still it turns out
письменность вы писали да русские ещё
lived in a swamp yes
получается в болото жили
you are on duty no
ты дежур нет
also from Mongolia brother no he is from Kazakh
тоже с Монголии брат нету он из Казах
damn what is interesting why everyone comes like that
блин что интересно что так все приезжают
and what kind of institute is this that takes from other
а что это за институт такой что с других
countries Russia yes yes yes yes here is a very
стран берёт Россию дадада да здесь очень
institute
институт
from the
из
fourteenth and the
четырнадцатого а
country is the fourteenth country there is
страна четырнадцатая страна есть
understood and how to enter there for example
понял а как поступить туда например это
anyone can enter or they somehow
любой может поступить или там как-то
select
отбирают
no first you in Mongolia participated in
нету вы сначала вы в Монголии участвовал
some kind of competition first healthy
соревнование какое-то сначала здоровый
then
потом
sports competitions to feel and
спортивный соревнованията чувствовать а
what competitions did you participate in
ты по каких соревнованиях участвовал
yes and how are you what competitions boxing
да а как ты какими соревнованиями бокс
what competition did you have no uh the most uh the
какое у тебя соревнование было нет ээ
most important is healthy if
самый ээ самый главный - это здоров если
your healthy is normal then you can and
твой здоров нормально тогда можно а
then aa more sporty is running  and
потом аа спортивней это вот бег и
pull up and so on yeah and do you have
подтягивать и так далее угу а у тебя
any relatives who are military in
кто-то из родственников военный в
Mongolia
Монголии
that you decided to be a military man too well a
что ты решил тоже военным быть
warrior no I understood why exactly you
ну воиным нету понял а почему именно
decided to go into the military
решил на военного идти
and I had long ago decided about this
а я раньше очень давно решил обы об этом
when I was a
я когда был
boy it was almost my dream
мальчик это почти мой моя мечта
and you yourself come from a city or from a village from a
а ты сам родом из города или из деревни
village from a small yes yes
из деревни из деревни из маленькой да да
very small I
очень маленький
understood lived there for 18 years then immediately came
понял там 18 лет жил потом сразу приехал
here that is you lived there for 18 years and
сюда а то есть ты сраз там 18 лет жил а
then one year lived in uh page no no
потом один го год жил в ээ странице а
no in the capital and then immediately yeah okay well
нет нет нет столице а потом сразу угу а
how did you find out that there is such an
хорошо а как ты узналто что есть такой
institute that you can come here to enroll well
институт что можно сюда приехать
there in the capital one year even a
ну там в столице один год вчисли даже
war
войны
institute so then immediately came
институт поэтому потом сразу приехал
here everything understood that is you in Mongolia
сюда всё понял то есть ты в Монголии
entered a military institute in the capital and
поступил в военный институт в столице а
then you were transferred here yeah yeah brought
потом тебя перевели сюда ага ага привели
and how how why exactly you were chosen
а как как почему именно тебя выбрали
I And why exactly you were chosen so that Well
я А почему тебя именно выбрали чтобы Ну
I was interested that is why if in the second
мне было интересно поэтому так если внич
world the institute then will be a very
миров у институт тогда будет очень
good officer I thought so I
хороший офицер я так думал
understood then it turns out after the institute you
понял потом получается после института
will return to
будешь возвращаться в
Mongolia yeah yeah of course I understood there will be
Монголию дада да конечно понял там будет
work obstrem and you already know guys
работать обстрем а ты знаешь уже ребят
who studied like that in Russia and
которые учились так в России и в
returned to Mongolia I dont
Монголию вернулись
know I dont know understood
не знаю не знаешь понял
but I I know that guys from North Korea are
а я я вот знаю что из Северной Кореи
sent to war in Ukraine
ребята отправляют на войну в Украину у
you dont send anyone from Mongolia yes no no no no no
вас из Монголии не отправляют никого да
and its better for the
ну и лучше чтобы
northerners yes
северникорес да
yes understood and how do you in Mongolia generally
да понял а как у вас в Монголии вообще
get the mood about this war that
получается настроение про эту войну что
people are talking
люди говорят
against his war yes
проти его войну да
I just think that its very bad in
это я просто думаю что это очень плохо
my opinion
по-моему
and other people think that its not more
а другие люди как думают никому не
useful to anyone than this war yes
полезне этого война да
other people even think so
другие люди даже так думают
everyone almost 850% in Mongolia what is the
все почти 850% в Монголии
population of Mongolia the
сколько населения Монголии
population is 3 million
население 3 млн
3 million so small does
3 млн такая маленькая
this mean that people from there can Yes
это значит что люди из жит могут Да
indeed yes yes 3.5 million yes yes yes 3
действительно да да 3,5 млн да да да 3
million 3.00.000
млн 3.00.000
then it turns out that its
то она получается она по территории
relatively large in territory and there are few people living yes yes
относительно большая а людей мало живёт
yes yes yes yes hmm I thought that
дадада дадада хм я что-то думал что
more of
больше
you in your city some kind of bombed
вы в вашей городе какой-то бомбрывал
yes there were in my city bombs exploded
да было в моём городе взрывались бомбы
flew oh-oh very many not very
прилетала ай-ай очень много не очень
many  because we fly far away
много потому что мы далеко прилетает
let's say
давай
we have cities cities that are closer to the
у нас есть города города которые ближе к
border that's where very often people fly
границе то там очень часто прилетает к
unfortunately
сожалению
this is native you meet Russians
это нативе ты встречаешься с русскими
yes yes I just happen to be with Russians here in chat
да да я же как раз с русскими тут в чат
roulette in general just say they all
рулетке обще как раз говорить они все
hate us they want Ukraine to be gone and
ненавидят нас они хотят чтобы Украины не
taken away listen and do you for
было забрали слушай а у вас
example have Mongols living in China there are Mongols on the
например в Китае живут монголы на
territory of China yes of course
территории Китая есть монголы да конечно
there are how many of them live there more than
есть сколько их там живёт больше чем
Mongolia or not no no no no well
Монголии или нет
now I'll look I do
нету нету нету а ну сейчас посмотрю
n't know for sure but there are
точно не знаю но есть
[music]
[музыка]
I'm even interested yes yes
мне аж интересно
I'm looking
дада я ищу
and in China 7 million
а в Китае 7 млн живёт
Mongols live well now it can't be not
монгольс а ну сейчас не может не
Mongols but specifically Mongolian now
монголов а именно монгольских сейчас
right now damn it's interesting because
сечас сейчас блин интересно так потому
I know that there are also a lot of Kazakhs in China
что я знаю что казахов тоже в Китае
there is Eastern Turkistan
много там восточный Туркистан
yes yes
да
yes 4 million in China in the Inner
да да 4 млн в Китае в регионе внутренняя
Mongolia region live in Liauin and so on yes that
Монголия живёт в Ляуине и так дальше да
is it turns out there are more Mongols in China than
то есть получается монголов в Китае
Mongols in Mongolia
больше чем монголов в Монголии
yes yes it turns out it's
да да так получается
interesting  yes
интересно да
and when China captured these territories
а когда Китай захватил эти территории
when I don't know a long time ago well
когда не знаю очень давно
you won't impose Russians
ну ты не наложишь русских
[music] you
[музыка]
won't impose I hate yes I hate
неналожишь ненавижу да я ненавижу
Russians because they want to kill me
русских потому что они хотят убить меня
they want to kill my people they yes
они хотят убить мой народ они да
some somewhere in the same way yes
какие-то где-то вмеча
listen and it turns out that if there are 3
да слушай а получается вот если вас 3
million of you yes how many armed forces do you have
млн да сколько у вас вооружённые силы
people
людей
I scored in my opinion
я забил по-моему
a little less than a thousand and less than a million
немного меньше тыся а меньше миллиона
no so of course less than a million
нет так конечно меньше миллиона потому
because if there are 3 million people then where
что если 3 млн людей то откуда там
will there be a million military yes
миллион военных будет да
yes in my opinion more more or less 500,000
да по-моему более более-менее 500.000
cool
прикольно
and the Mongols who now the youth
а монголы которые вот сейчас молодёжь
what other than Mongolian what language do they
какой кроме монгольского какой язык
study second Russian
изучают второй русский
and no no no not Russian Russian English
а нет нет нет не не русский русский
English English understood
английский английский английский понял
yes and where do the youth go to which
да а молодёжь куда выезжает в какие
countries mainly
страны в основном
and to which countries do the youth go to work to
а в какие страны молодёжь едет работать
study in Mongolia yes from Mongolia did
учиться в Монголии да из Монголии
not understand again
не поняли опять
uh from Mongolia young people
ээ из Монголии молодые люди в какие
go to which countries like you to Russia yes
страны едут вот как ты в Россию да
went to study where they go to study to
поехал учиться куда едут учиться
work
работать
and South Korea in  South Korea yes yes there are a
а Южней Кореи в Южную Корею да да там
lot of people living there who are from
очень много люди живут которые из
Mongolia
Монголии
interesting cool yes fairies Australia
интересно прикольно да фей Австралия
because Australia and the vision is so
потому что Австралия а визия такая
easy what is
лёгкая чем
left cool interesting and how for example
остал прикольно интересно а как например
uh your well let's say people see the future of
ээ ваши ну скажем люди видят будущее
Mongolia rich poor will it be like and the
Монголии богатая бедная будет она как а
future I think that it is very rich and at the
будущей я думаю что очень богат а за
expense of what at the expense of what it can
счёт чего за счёт чего она богатая может
be rich
быть
for what well yes and and because of what Mongolia
за что ну да и и из-за чего Монголия
can be rich what should it do
может быть богатой что она должна делать
to become rich there are
чтобы стать богатый
many factories you build then it will be
много завод есть строите тогда будет
very buggy well
очень багать
factories and what to do at these factories at
ну заводы а что делать на этих заводах
these factories it is cold and so on
на этих заводах это колд и так далее
a lot of metals and I understand the mining
много металлей а понял горнодобывающая
industry to mine gold yeah yeah yeah
промышленность золото добывать да угу да
gold I understood that is you have there uh mountain
золото понял то есть у вас там ээ горные
ranges and there are different metals there that
массивы и там есть разные металлы
can be dug up yeah yeah I
которые можно выкапывать да да да
understood interesting uh
понял интересно э вот это этих металлей
you could not use these metals at all
вы могли вообще не использовать
just export
просто экспорт
and you get it you have everything basically
а у вас получается у вас всё в основном
flat steppe yeah and there are rivers
степь ровная да да
that rivers there is a
что реки есть
river and yes there are there are many or few
река а да есть есть много или мало
yeah many
да много
interesting the biggest river goes  aa in
интересно самый большой река идёт аа в
Beka
Бека
Baikal I flow yeah yeah what is it called Seling
байкал впадаю угу да как она называется
Selinga se yes Selinga Russia they
селинг селинга се да селинга россия они
call it Selinga yeah yeah there was gold
её селинга называют да да там же золото
mining on Selinga
добыча была на селинге
on Selinga gold was mined yeah on Selinga
на селинге золото добывали да на селинге
in my opinion yeah and what does Selinga mean in
по-моему да а что означает селинга по
your language
вашему языку
what does Selinga mean in your language
что на вашем языке селинга что означает
just Selinga it's in Mongolian and
просто селинг это на монгольском языке а
what does this word mean it
что означает это слово
means that it is very big and wide
значит что это очень большой и широкий
understood and Baikal is not a Mongolian
понял а Байкал - это не монгольское
name no yeah
название нет
it's not a Mongolian name it's a Turkic yeah yeah
да это не монгольское называ это тюрское
understood yeah and how do you feel about
угу понял да а как вы относитесь к
Kazakhs other Turks
казахам к другим к тюркам
Ktyushki and what is it well about Kazakhs
ктюшкам и то что такое ну к казахи
Uzbeks how do you feel about them and
узбеки к ним как относитесь
if there is yeah yeah
а если есть да угу
how do you feel about them and I do
как относиться и
n't know either
не знаю тоже
and what do you think Russia can fight with
а как ты считаешь Россия может воевать с
China
Китаем
no they can't why
нет не могут почему
ask well
спроси
could Russia fight with China or
ну Россия могла бы воевать с Китаем или
not
нет
Russia could I do
россия могла
n't understand
не поня
Russia could a war start between Russia and
россия может начаться война России и
China
Китая
but no  in my opinion it won't happen but Russia and
а нету по-моему не будет а Россия и
America maybe will and or America and
Америка может быть будет и или Америка и
China will happen in my opinion so I think that
Китай будет по-моему так думаю
is Russia and China won't fight
то есть Россия с Китаем не будет воевать
yes yes I
да да
understand I just
понял я просто так
think that are you writing or what, not just
думаю ты что пишишься что ли не просто
reading the news on your phone and
читаю новости на телефоне а
what just seems to me that there is a war no but it
что просто мне кажется что война нет но
seems to me that Russia and China will
мне кажется что Россия с Китаем будет
fight because the Far East is
воевать потому что Дальний Восток это
all Chinese lands before yeah yeah Russia
всё китайские земли раньше были угу
captured it
россия захватила
so
так что
now when Russia
сейчас когда Россия
weakens a war will start there in the Far
ослабнет начнётся война там на Дальнем
East there are a lot of Chinese really yes a
Востоке китайцев очень много правда
lot so
да очень много так
ok let's run for now ok so that's how
что хорошо давай побегу
you see yes
вот так бачите да
Russia in its military universities trains people
россия в своих вузах военных учит людей
from Mongolia from Kazakhstan from other countries
из Монголии из Казахстана из других
essentially the FSB and other agencies yes already have
сути ФСБ и другие органы да уже имеют
access to
доступ к
future foreign military specialists
будущим иностранным военным специалистам
who will be officers there and so on so
которые будут там офицерами и так дальше
now he is suffering somewhere there is
вот он сейчас мучится там где-то на него
collecting a
собирает
folder for him somewhere there is recruiting
папочку там где-то вербовочку проводит
somewhere someone that is maybe not everyone
да где-то кого-то то есть может не всех
yes but then the person grows up
да но вот потом человек вырастает
he gets up for himself makes a career and the folder is
он себе встаёт карьеру делает а папочка
on him  somewhere there is something
на него где-то лежит где-то что-то там
incriminating evidence, something from parties,
компроматики какие-то что-то с вечеринок
and so on, so yes,
и так дальше так
subscribe to my Instagram, I dont know
підпишись на мій Instagram я не знаю для
why you are there, why else are you there to
чого це тобі для чого ще тобі там
marvel at Face, but for you, either, or
дивитись на Face але для тебе це оди або
three
три
clicks support me and I will say:
клика підтримаєш мене и я буду казати:
Wow, theres a lot of beauty in me  followers and I
"Вау в мене там купа фоловерів и в мене
will have a great
буде класний
mood, subscribe to my Instagram
настро круті підпишись на мій Instagram
pop Andriy,
попик Андрій
so let me check for you"
отак давай я тебе чекаю"